Reverend Dharma Friends, the Bodhi Mind of
Kính thưa các quý Đạo Hữu Tâm Bồ Đề của
the Buddhas of the Ten Directions never ceases. The
Mười Phương Chư Phật không bao giờ dứt
Bodhi Mind of the Bodhisattvas continues to
Tâm Bồ Đề của chư Bồ Tát nối tiếp thúc
urge us to cultivate the Bodhi Mind.
giục chúng ta hãy Phát Tâm Bồ Đề
Even if one does not yet understand the
dù ai chưa hiểu về Tâm Bồ Đề nhưng nghe
Bodhi Mind, upon hearing its benefits for
thấy lợi ích của Tâm Bồ Đề đối với sự
achieving enlightenment for oneself and
thành tựu đạo quả cho mình
for the great enlightenment of the multitude of
đối với sự giác ngộ to lớn cho số đông
sentient beings, simply
chúng sinh
hearing it and joyfully
chỉ cần nghe thấy thôi mà mình Hoan Hỷ
cultivating the Bodhi Mind will bring immeasurable merit and blessings. For transcendental Dharma,
Phát Tâm Bồ Đề theo thì công đức Phước
just
đối với các pháp xuất thế gian thì chỉ
one such joyful cultivation of the Bodhi Mind
một lần hoan hỷ phát tâm như vậy thì
will enable one to cultivate the Bodhi Mind for many lifetimes and eons, leading to the attainment of the supreme enlightenment.
nhiều đời nhiều kiếp mình sẽ được Phát
Just one such joyful moment of cultivating the Bodhi Mind brings
Chánh Giác chỉ một niệm hoan hỉ như vậy
blessings
chúng ta phát tâm thì Phước báo đó
greater than even the blessings of the heavenly realms. Therefore, the
lớn hơn cả Phước báo của cõi trời cho
Bodhi Mind, as taught by the Buddha, is the wet nurse
nên Tâm Bồ Đề Đức phật có dạy là Nhũ mẫu
of all Buddhas; the Bodhi Mind gives birth
của chư Phật tức là Tâm Bồ Đề sinh ra
to the Buddhas, enabling the attainment of Buddhahood. The Bodhi
Chư Phật Tâm Bồ Đề khiến thành tựu Phật
Mind contains perfect contemplation. May the
quả tâm chứa Hoàn quán mong rằng với sự
joy in our hearts, upon
hoan hỷ ở trong lòng khi chúng ta được
hearing this song, inspire
nghe ca khúc vì lợi ích chúng sinh hãy
us to cultivate the Bodhi Mind for the benefit of all sentient beings.
Phát Tâm Bồ Đề khiến cho chúng ta có
With joy and longing to
được tâm hoan hỷ và sự mong mỏi để được
cultivate Bodhicitta, if anyone simply achieves the
Phát Tâm Bồ Đề nếu như ai chỉ cần thành
aspiration to participate in the
tựu được niệm mong mỏi
Bodhicitta Awakening Ceremony, that person
dự lễ Phát Tâm Bồ Đề thì người đó chắc
will surely strive for Bodhi and soon reside in the
chắn sẽ tinh tấn bồ đề sẽ sớm trụ ở Tâm
Bodhicitta Mind. Wishing all fellow practitioners always strive
Bồ Đề chúc các quý đạo hữu luôn luôn
diligently, and may we all achieve pure mindfulness and
tinh tấn và tất cả chúng ta thành tựu
attain supreme Bodhicitta
được niệm thanh tịnh cầu vô thượng bồ đề
during the Bodhicitta Awakening Ceremony on
trong buổi lễ Phát Tâm Bồ Đề vào ngày 19
June 19th at Ba Vang Temple in the morning.
tháng 6 tại chùa Ba Vàng vào buổi sáng
Wishing all fellow practitioners and their families
kính chúc các quý đạo hữu và gia đình vô
boundless peace and happiness. Namo Buddha Shakyamuni.
lượng an lạc Nam Mô Phật Bổn Sư Thích Ca
Bodhicitta Mind.
Tâm Bồ Đề
If anyone asks,
Nếu Ai Có Hỏi
Bodhicitta Mind is noble and exalted.
Tâm Bồ Đề là tăng cao quý
Towards truth,
Hướng về chân lý
above, seeking Buddhahood, below, saving sentient beings.
trên cầu thành Phật dưới độ chúng sinh
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
Loving all, sacrificing and
yêu thương hết tất cả
flourishing without thinking of
hi sinh cùng phất phà không nghĩ suy cho
oneself. The
riêng mình
Bodhicitta Mind suffers, the Bodhicitta Mind is compassionate, the profound truth, the
kìa thầy chúng sinh Khổ Tâm Bồ Đề thao
enlightenment of sentient beings. [
thương Nghi Huyền sát ngộ chúng sinh
Music]
[âm nhạc]
In this world, even with wealth in hand,
ở nơi thế gian này dù phụ quý trong tay
even intoxicated by fame, one will still suffer
Dù say men danh vọng rồi cũng sẽ đau khổ
because impermanence steals it away. Happiness also comes and goes. I
bởi vô thường cướp đi Hạnh Phúc Cũng
will fight for true happiness. The
Chia Ly con sẽ đấu tranh hạnh phúc thật
six realms of reincarnation, sentient beings die
lục đạo Luân Hồi này chúng sinh chết ở
here and are reborn into another life, forever suffering
đây tái sinh vào Kiếp kia mãi mãi chịu
separation.  Enduring suffering forever
chia lìa mãi mãi chịu khổ đau
[music]
[âm nhạc]
brings happiness to sentient beings
mang đến cho chúng sinh
in dreams,
hạnh phúc trong giấc mộng
only more than Bodhi, many nights for sentient beings,
chỉ còn hơn Bồ Đề bao đêm cho chúng sinh
peace, true happiness in the record
bình yên chân hạnh phúc nơi biên bản
[music]
[âm nhạc]
[Applause]
[Vỗ tay]
for my happiness, for the
vì hạnh phúc của mình
happiness of sentient beings,
vì hạnh phúc chúng sinh
for the enlightenment of truth, let the mind be tearless, for the happiness of sentient beings,
vì giác ngộ chân lý hãy phát tâm vô lệ
let the happiness of sentient beings be missed, let the
vì hạnh phúc Chúng Sinh hãy bỏ lỡ một
happiness of sentient beings be awakened,
hạnh phúc Chúng Sinh hãy Phát Tâm Bồ Đề
for the happiness of sentient beings, let the Bodhi mind be awakened,
vì hạnh phúc Chúng Sinh hãy Phát Tâm Bồ
then happiness of sentient beings, let the
Đề thì hạnh phúc Chúng Sinh hãy Phát Tâm
happiness of sentient beings be awakened ... entered into life
vì hạnh phúc Chúng Sinh hãy vào đời
[music]
[âm nhạc]